<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <titlepage>

        <author>
            <personname>Leonid Kovalev</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>Syracuse University</institution>
            <email>lvkovale@syr.edu</email>
        </author>

        <date><today /></date>

    </titlepage>


    <acknowledgement xml:id="acknowledgement">

        <p>The following textbooks were helpful in preparation of these notes.<ul>
            <li><p><url href="https://ebookcentral-proquest-com.libezproxy2.syr.edu/lib/syracuse-ebooks/detail.action?docID=953183">Numerical Methods: Using MATLAB</url> by George Lindfield and John Penny</p></li>
            <li><p><url href="https://epubs-siam-org.libezproxy2.syr.edu/doi/book/10.1137/9780898719987">A First Course in Numerical Methods</url> by Uri M. Ascher and Chen Greif </p></li>
            <li><p><url href="https://syracuse.summon.serialssolutions.com/2.0.0/link?t=1603042996399">Approximation Theory and Approximation Practice</url> by Lloyd N. Trefethen</p></li>
            <li><p><url href="https://www.mathworks.com/moler/chapters.html">Numerical Computing with MATLAB</url> by Clive Moler</p></li>
        </ul></p>

    </acknowledgement>

    <preface xml:id="preface">

        <p>The topics covered in this course can be divided into 5 units.<ol>
    <li><p>Matlab: Matrix/vector manipulation, matrix/vector creation, elementwise operations, built-in functions, input/output, 2d graphics, scripting, functions.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solving equations: linear systems, bisection method, fixed point method, Newton and secant methods, multivariable Newton's method, Broyden's method.</p></li>
    <li><p>Numerical calculus: numerical differentiation, numerical integration: trapezoidal rule, Simpson's rule, orthogonal polynomials (Legendre, Laguerre), Gaussian integration, Gauss-Laguerre integration, adaptive integration, solving ODE with Euler's method and trapezoidal method, ODE systems.</p></li>
    <li><p>Data fitting: polynomial interpolation, spline interpolation, discrete Fourier transform, linear least squares, model comparison, nonlinear least squares, transforming data. </p></li>
    <li><p>Optimization: linear programming, single-variable minimization, steepest descent, conjugate gradient method, Nelder-Mead method, constrained optimization, applications.</p></li></ol></p>
 
 <p>Numerical linear algebra is not included above because it is the subject of a separate course (MAT 532).</p> 

 <p>Although the course is built around Matlab software, one can use <url href="https://www.gnu.org/software/octave/download.html">Octave</url> to run examples and do homework just as well.</p>

<p>If you are new to Matlab, begin with the free online minicourse <url href="https://matlabacademy.mathworks.com/R2021a/portal.html?course=gettingstarted">MATLAB Onramp</url>. The first part of the course, up to and including <q>Plotting Data</q>, is the most important one. It will be referenced in each of the first four chapters/classes.</p>

    </preface>
  
</frontmatter>
